<?xml version="1.0" ?><gallery><album id="1" title="The courtroom, Duane Harms and his wife, Judy" lgPath="images/part9/lg/" tnPath="images/part9/tn/" thumb=""><img src="1.jpg" title="" caption="The Union Pacific's City of Denver streamliner idles on the tracks near LaSalle after it smashed into the school bus. The lead locomotive sustained relatively minor damage in the crash, which demolished the bus and killed 20 children. (COLORADO STATE PATROL/1961)" /><img src="2.jpg" title="" caption="Defense attorney Jim Shelton addresses Judge Donald Carpenter during the manslaughter trial of school bus driver Duane Harms, seated to the right of Shelton. Behind Shelton are prosecutors Karl Ahlborn and Bill Bohlender. (MIKE O'MEARA/ROCKY MOUNTAIN NEWS/1962)" /><img src="3.jpg" title="" caption="One of defense attorney Jim Shelton's trial exhibits shows the angle at which the road and the tracks intersected. Bus driver Duane Harms, coming from the east, had to twist around in his seat and look behind him to see if a train was approaching. (COURTESY VIRGINIA SHELTON)" /><img src="4.jpg" title="" caption="This photo depicts the view from a bus stopped at the crossing. From the driver's seat, the rails appear in the fourth and fifth windows on the right side of the bus. On Dec. 14, 1961, those windows were frosted because of the 6-degree temperature. (COLORADO STATE PATROL/1961)" /><img src="5.jpg" title="" caption="The Union Pacific City of Denver streamliner approaches the crossing in this photograph taken in early 1962. Depending on where a driver stopped, the utility poles could obscure the view of an approaching train. (WELD COUNTY DISTRICT ATTORNEY/1962)" /><img src="6.jpg" title="" caption="This view west toward the crossing shows the house of Jerry Baxter, left, and farmer Albert Bindel's home, right. Bindel stepped out into his yard and looked to the west moments before the train-bus collision and believed driver Duane Harms had stopped. (WELD COUNTY DISTRICT ATTORNEY/1961)" /><img src="7.jpg" title="" caption="This photograph, used as a defense exhibit, shows attorney Jim Shelton, right, and bus driver Duane Harms, just behind him wearing the bus driver's hat, in a school bus at the crossing with three unidentified men. (COURTESY VIRGINIA SHELTON)" /><img src="8.jpg" title="" caption="Defense attorney Jim Shelton, left, stands outside court with bus driver Duane Harms; his wife, Judy; and his parents, Wilber and Lavena Harms, on Jan. 2, 1962, after Harms' arraignment. Shelton, who was appointed to represent Harms, threw all his legal experience into the case against the young bus driver. (BILL PEERY/ROCKY MOUNTAIN NEWS/1962)" /></album><action type="on" bin="chapter9_dim.jpg" /><part num="9" nt="nine" /><parttitle><![CDATA[TRIAL]]></parttitle><stphoto url="images/sample9.jpg" /><inventors name="TRIAL"><![CDATA[Did Duane Harms stop at the crossing? His manslaughter trial tries to answer that question.]]></inventors><headline><![CDATA[A story about Duane Harms]]></headline><byline><![CDATA[Kevin Vaughan]]></byline><photo url="images/part9/story9.jpg" /><photocredit credit="Mike O'Meara &#169; Rocky Mountain News/1962" /><caption><![CDATA[Jim Shelton, court-appointed attorney for Duane Harms, argues before Judge Donald Carpenter during the bus driver's trial in March 1962.]]></caption><abstract><![CDATA[Did Duane Harms stop at the crossing? His manslaughter trial tries to answer that question.]]></abstract><story><![CDATA[<p>In the weeks after school bus driver Duane Harms was charged with manslaughter, nearly four dozen letters landed on the desk of prosecutor Karl Ahlborn in Greeley.</p><p>Some handwritten, some typed on onion-skin paper, they all came from people touched deeply by the tragedy of Dec. 14, 1961.A few urged harsh action against Harms.</p><p><em>I think the driver of the bus should be made an example for needless manslaughter. I don't see how he can live with himself knowing he was to blame as a reckless piece of humanity.</em></p><p><em>Unsigned, from Spokane, Wash.</em></p><p>Several blasted the Union Pacific railroad.</p><p><em>I wonder why it is that the railroads are always right when they kill people at railroad crossings and the drivers in automobiles and trucks are always to blame.</em></p><p><em>An observer and resident of Colorado</em></p><p>Many more &#151; 30 in all &#151; expressed support and compassion for Harms.</p><p><em>For two years I had the privilege of hiring Duane and I can tell you very honestly he was one of the few boys I have hired that I allowed to drive my pickup and car ... In my opinion this fine young man deserves better treatment than he has had. I am sure you will be kind as well as just.</em></p><p><em>Norris Pyle, Fleming</em></p><p><em>My son will testify for him if needed for there doesn't have to be a court of law to punish him &#151; he has to live with this his self. That's enough.</em></p><p><em>Dorris Collins Briles, Greeley</em></p><p><em>I only felt the urge to write this letter to you, so you may convey the wishes and the devoted prayers of a Methodist minister down in Texas, and pray all charges, ill will, and injustice shall be withdrawn from this young man, Mr. Duane Harms.</em></p><p><em>Travis L. Darby, Port Arthur, Texas</em></p><p>But the letters did not deter prosecutor Ahlborn. Neither did the parents who urged him to let Harms go free, even though their children had been on the bus.</p><p>And so the manslaughter trial of Duane R. Harms, case No. 5815, began quietly on March 20, 1962, at the stately Weld County courthouse in downtown Greeley.</p><p>That Tuesday morning, 130 potential jurors climbed the 67 marble steps to the fourth floor and Judge Donald Carpenter's courtroom. Barely three months had passed since the deadliest traffic accident in Colorado history. Six miles separated the courthouse from the crossing where it happened.</p><p>Hours of questions, challenges and decisions ended with 10 men and two women chosen to decide whether Harms committed a crime at the crossing.</p><p>They would have to answer, in essence, one question: Did Harms stop and look on Dec. 14, 1961, in the moments before a high-speed passenger train tore through his school bus?</p><p>The jurors selected as their foreman Alan "Bud" Middaugh, a 32-year-old cattle buyer for the Monfort family. He wanted the job, and the others were relieved when he agreed to do it.</p><p>It had been a long day for everyone, an even longer one for Harms, 23 years old with a daughter born just months earlier. Before it ended, Weld County Sheriff Bob Welsh handed Harms two summonses. He had been named a defendant &#151; along with the school district, Union Pacific and train engineer Herbert F. Sommers &#151; in a $75,000 lawsuit filed by the families of three children who had died.</p><p>At 9:30 the next morning, everyone was back in court.</p><p>Prosecutor Ahlborn went first.</p><p>Harms, he said, was guilty because he didn't take the time to be careful. Because he didn't bother to look at a railroad signal light 728 feet east of the crossing, which clicked on 30 seconds before the train's headlight came into view.</p><p>Because he didn't bother to look for that burning headlight, visible for 2 1/2 minutes before the train could be seen.</p><p>And because he didn't bother to look for the train, which was visible for 44 seconds before it ripped his school bus in two.</p><p>Jim Shelton, Harms' court-appointed attorney, stood. He was determined to stop his young client's life from being ruined by a mistake he believed anyone could have made. Harms, he said, followed all the rules in his manual.</p><p>"He was totally unaware a train was approaching," Shelton said. "Duane Harms had no consciousness that his acts would harm the passengers on his bus. If he did anything wrong, it did not constitute criminal negligence."</p><p><b>'Poor little children'</b></p><p>Parents &#151; some who had lost children, some who hadn't &#151; sat quietly in the back of the courtroom as a series of prosecution witnesses took their turns on the stand.</p><p>A Union Pacific supervisor described the speed tape locked in the locomotive cab that showed the train had approached the crossing at 79 mph, the limit on that stretch of tracks.</p><p>Sommers, the 64-year-old engineer, said Harms had slowed, but not stopped, at the crossing.</p><p>"The windows were frosted up, but not so much you couldn't see those poor little children down there," he said. "You couldn't recognize them ... just sort of see images."</p><p>State Trooper Don Girnt walked jurors through the scene, recounting his measurements and calculations.</p><p>Thursday came, and Girnt returned to the stand, followed by four other detectives. All said that in their initial questioning of <p>Harms, he seemed unsure whether he had stopped at the crossing.</p><p>Ahlborn rested his case. He and Deputy District Attorney Bill Bohlender had called 13 witnesses.</p><p>Shelton opened the defense with Albert Bindel. The farmer told the jurors how he'd been outside when the bus passed, how he'd heard the train approaching and looked west toward the crossing.</p><p>"As near as I could tell, the bus was stopped at the crossing," he testified. "The red lights, about halfway down on the bus, were on.</p><p>"I came to the conclusion he was stopped, and I went into the house to take my children to school."</p><p><b>A parent speaks</b></p><p>Then Art Larson, a slender 6-footer, stepped to the witness stand and raised his right hand, ready to swear to God to tell the truth.</p><p>A truck driver and farmer of Swedish descent, Arthur Gustav Larson may have seemed an unlikely defense witness, for he had experienced the full range of emotions since Dec. 14, 1961.</p><p>Thankfulness, that his daughter, Linda, had stayed home with a cold and missed the bus.</p><p>Relief, that his daughter, Alice, was recovering from a crushed gallbladder and torn liver and appendix.</p><p>Heartbreak, that his son, Steve, had died.</p><p>Other parents had abandoned Harms. They'd threatened him, pushed for jail time.</p><p>But Larson had not. He had not forgotten how careful Harms had always been, how much he had helped soothe Steve as the awkward boy struggled to fit in among the other kids. He had not forgotten the courage Harms had shown four days after the accident, visiting Alice in the hospital. She awakened from her coma while Harms was in her room.</p><p>Larson had been in a unique position, just moments before the train hit the bus, to answer the question that could determine Harms' fate.</p><p>He told the jurors about sending Alice and Steve to catch the bus, about getting into his delivery truck to take his oldest daughter, Nancy, into Greeley, where she attended College High.</p><p>He told them how he'd pulled up to the railroad tracks just as the streamliner flashed by him. He told them how he had looked to the west to see the bus stopped at the next crossing, a little more than half a mile away.</p><p>"I had no doubt," he testified. "I was sure the bus stopped, and that he'd seen the train, so I went on to town."</p> <p>Jerry Hembry, a 16-year-old whose wrestling season ended when the collision tore apart his shoulder, was just as firm.</p><p>"The bus stopped," he testified. "I didn't hear the train whistle or see anything."</p><p>On Friday morning &#151; Day Four &#151; Harms put on a coat and tie again and headed to the courthouse. The jurors &#151; and the families of many of the dead children &#151; would hear his version of events.</p><p>"I usually stop, open the door, listen, then turn around and raise up so I can see over the kids," he testified. "Then I look in the mirror."</p><p>It was, he told the jurors, "a normal morning." Under questioning from Shelton, he said he specifically remembered that he opened the door, turned in his seat and tried to look down the tracks. He said his vision was obscured by frost on the bus windows. He said he did not remember the actual crash.</p><p>"When I remember, I recall lying down in front of the bus," he said quietly. "It looked like it had been cut off or blown off, I didn't know which.</p><p>"I walked back around the bus and saw the train down the track. Then I knew what had happened."</p><p>And so it went for hours. Harms did not break down. He did not back down, either, insisting that he must have stopped at the crossing.</p><p>Friday afternoon came, but the trial ground on. Rebuttal witnesses testified. Shelton and Ahlborn took turns with closing arguments. Judge Carpenter read 19 pages of instructions to the 10 men and two women of the jury.</p><p>Finally, at 9:58 p.m., the case was theirs.</p><p><b>NEXT:</b> Verdict</p>]]></story><videos text="part9/videoText9.swf" still="part9/still9.jpg"><headline><![CDATA[TRIAL]]></headline><byline><![CDATA[Video by Tim Skillern]]></byline><intro><![CDATA[Jury foreman Bud Middaugh talks about the trial.]]></intro><video url="part9/titleLow.flv" /><video url="part9/titleMedium.flv" /><video url="part9/titleHigh.flv" /></videos><documents><link type="pdf" url="images/part9/docs/prosecutor_notes.pdf"><![CDATA[Notes from Weld County prosecutor Karl Ahlborn's file]]></link><link type="pdf" url="images/part9/docs/jury_instructions.pdf"><![CDATA[Instructions to the jury in Duane Harms' manslaughter trial]]></link><link type="pdf" url="images/part9/docs/da_letters.pdf"><![CDATA[A sampling of dozens of letters to the Weld County District Attorney's Office]]></link></documents><related></related><sources><link url="images/part9/docs/Chapter9_anno.pdf"><![CDATA[Sources link]]></link></sources><inprint><link url="images/part9/docs/print09.pdf"><![CDATA[PDF to actual print story]]></link></inprint><chat url="http://blogs.rockymountainnews.com/denver/rockytalklive/archives/2007/02/test_1.html" /></gallery>
